<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuites shifts, and euasions; or, his deportment in controuersies of religion. Or, A treatise, wherein the causes are examined why Mr. Arnoux the Iesuite, refuseth to answere to seauenteene questions propounded by the ministers of the church of Paris Wherein also the treatise of fiue euasions which he hath added to the examination of our confession, is likewise examined and answered: by Peter Du Moulin.</title>
            <title>Fuites et évasions du Sieur Arnoux. English</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846496</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1064:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuites shifts, and euasions; or, his deportment in controuersies of religion. Or, A treatise, wherein the causes are examined why Mr. Arnoux the Iesuite, refuseth to answere to seauenteene questions propounded by the ministers of the church of Paris Wherein also the treatise of fiue euasions which he hath added to the examination of our confession, is likewise examined and answered: by Peter Du Moulin.</title>
                  <title>Fuites et évasions du Sieur Arnoux. English</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Starre in Cornehill, and in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Fuites et évasions du Sieur Arnoux.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Intended as a supplement to Du Moulin's "The buckler of the faith", second edition (STC 7314).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arnoux, Jean, d. 1636 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Eglises réformées de France. --  Confession de foy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11469:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11469:1"/>
            <p>THE IESVITES SHIFTS, AND EVASIONS; OR, His deportment in Controuerſies of RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A Treatiſe, wherein the cauſes are examined why M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> the Ieſuite, refuſeth to anſwere to ſeauenteene queſtions propounded by the Miniſters of the Church of PARIS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein alſo the Treatiſe of fiue euaſions which he hath</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the examination of our confeſſion, is likewiſe examined and anſwered: <hi>BY</hi> PETER DV MOVLIN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Starre in <hi>Cornehill,</hi> and in <hi>Popes-Head-Alley.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11469:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11469:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, I would not haue thee to imagine, that our Author would haue vouchſafed to beſtow his labour vpon the confutation of ſuch ſilly ſhifts and ſorry Euaſions as our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Engliſh Jeſuites and Popiſh Prieſts ſucke out of their fathers plants, and caſt foorth with more malice then wit, in paltry pamphlets amongſt vs, to ſeduce ſimple people; for, alas, they are not worthy any wiſe mans view; much leſſe his paines for confutation. But theſe of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Arnoux</hi> are of an higher ſtraine, and of more eſpeciall moment; which being fully cleared and diſplayed by our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Author, and added as a Supplement to his <hi>Buckler of Faith,</hi> a Booke that is now re-printed, as moſt neceſſary and profitable, in theſe diſputing times, I could not with-hold this peece from thee any longer, becauſe I ſuppoſed it would be very vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:11469:3"/> vnto thee alſo, as a light Sword to offend our common Aduerſaries, the more readily in lighter skirmiſhes either ioyntly with, or ſeuerally without the <hi>Buckler;</hi> which is fit to defend vs in our ſtrongeſt Incounters with them; I doubt not (good Reader) but thou ſhalt in both of them finde ſuch ſatisfaction as ſhall giue thee great content, and make thee ſtand the more ſtedfeſtly and boldly in the breach againſt the enemies aſſaults, amidſt a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſtaggerers and backe-ſliders, which that thou maiſt be inabled to do, to the glory of God, and the ſaluation of thy own ſoule, I ſhall alwayes pray, and indeuour my ſelfe to yeeld thee what helpe I am able; <hi>Vale.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11469:3"/>
            <head>THE IESVITES SHIFTS AND EVASIONS: OR, His deportment in Controuerſies of RELIGION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The demaunds of the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Paris,</hi> made to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Arnoux</hi> the Ieſuite.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more eaſier than to propound queſtions, but the difficulty conſiſteth in anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring well. An ignorant perſon will put more queſtions in an houre, than a wiſe man can ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue in a yeare. A knot is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knit, but it is not ſo eaſily vnknit againe: from thence it proceedeth that in Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie for Religion, he that feeleth himſelfe to be too weake, or that his cauſe is ill-grounded, alwaies ſeekes to make difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to finde ſome meanes to blame his aduerſaries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, but as much as he can, or may, exempteth himſelfe from yeelding a reaſon of his owne faith, and is wary to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any proofe of his Religion.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:11469:4"/>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Gontri</hi> late deceaſed, giueth this counſell in a booke which he made touching the manner how to confer with vs: for, hauing by experience found how dangerous it is to be too forward, &amp; that the ſureſt meanes is to bind vs to proue that which we ſay, and ſtill to finde ſome cauilation in our confeſſion, he giueth this counſell to his Diſciples, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be warie how to make anſwere to our demaunds, or to defend themſelues againſt our accuſations, and neuer to enter into a proofe of the Catholicke Romiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>This counſell liketh Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> exceeding well: for hauing, in the preſence of his Maieſtie, ſnatcht at the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of the confeſſion of our faith, and exclaimed againſt ſome cotations of the places of the Scripture by vs noted, he preſſeth vs to defend them, and to iuſtifie our allegations. And hath made a booke wherein hee diſciphereth our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the faith, from the one end to the other.</p>
               <p>Which booke, and all his accuſations, wee hope we haue in ſome ſort ſatisfied, whereby I am perſwaded that he will not hereafter enter ſo eaſily into the liſts againe. And not content to defend our ſelues, we haue taken on vs the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengers part, and haue alſo preſſed him to defend his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſee if he hath ſo much capacitie in him to anſwere, as he hath readineſſe to put queſtions.</p>
               <p>And in counterchange of that, which he doth, ſeeking to ſnatch at the places of Scripture noted in the margent of our confeſſion, we haue produced the allegations of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uagant <hi>vnam ſanctam,</hi> made by <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. and the places of Scripture, alledged by the laſt Councell of <hi>Lateran:</hi> as for example, the Apoſtles hauing ſaid, <hi>here are two ſwords:</hi> the Lord made anſwere and ſaid, <hi>It is enough.</hi> And in the beginning of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> it is ſaid, that <hi>in the beginning God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heauen and earth.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. it is ſaid, <hi>all the Kings of the earth ſhall worſhip him:</hi> And Ieſus Chriſt ſaid, <hi>all power is giuen me in heauen, and in earth, Math.</hi> 28.18. which places and many the like, are vſed by the ſaid Pope, and that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, to proue that the Pope hath ſoueraigne power, as well ouer temporall, as ouer ſpirituall things, and that Kings muſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11469:4"/> worſhip him, and that he hath all power in heauen and in earth. Whereupon we aske Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> whether he will approue ſuch allegations: or, whether in the margents of our confeſſion he findeth any places of Scripture noted with ſuch horrible licentiouſneſſe, and manifeſt prophanation.</p>
               <p>And in counterchange, for asking vs a proofe of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the Word of God, we ſummon, and defie him, to proue his Religion by the Word of God, and to that end haue propounded theſe ſeauenteene queſtions following vnto him.</p>
               <p n="1">1 In what place of the holy Scriptures God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to call vpon dead Saints.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Where God hath commaunded vs to repreſent the Trinity in ſtone or in picture.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In what place of the holy Scripture, we are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to worſhip and ſerue the Images of Saints, or to adore them, as it is ordained by the ſecond Councell of Nice.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In what place of the Scripture it is commaunded to ſacrifice the body of Ieſus Chriſt in the Euchariſt, and where Ieſus Chriſt eſtabliſhed ſacrificators of his body.</p>
               <p n="5">5 In what place of the Scripture God hath commanded to withhold the Cup from the people in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="6">6 In what place of the Scripture, the Biſhop of Rome is eſtabliſhed and made S. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, in qualitie of head of the Church.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Where God commaundeth vs, in the Church to reade the holy Scriptures to the people, in a language which they vnderſtand not.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Where God hath commaunded vs to pray vnto God, without vnderſtanding what we pray, praying in a language that he which prayeth vnderſtandeth not.</p>
               <p n="9">9 In what place of the Scripture, it is ſaid, that the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt hath ſatisfied for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and for the fault of ſinnes committed before baptiſme, but touching the puniſhment for ſinnes committed after baptiſme, it belongeth vnto vs to ſatisfie the iuſtice of God, either in this life, or in purgatorie.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11469:5"/>10 Where God forbiddeth Prieſts and Monkes to marry.</p>
               <p n="11">11 In what place of the Scripture we are commanded to adore the reliques of Saints.</p>
               <p n="12">12 In what place of the Scripture there is any thing ſaid of the place of <hi>Limbus</hi> for little Children.</p>
               <p n="13">13 In what place of the Scripture it is ſaid, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Soueraigne Iudge of doubts in faith, and that ſhe cannot erre.</p>
               <p n="14">14 In what place of the Scripture the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is called Queene of Heauen.</p>
               <p n="15">15 In what place of the Scripture God forbiddeth the people to reade the holy Scriptures without ſpeciall permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p n="16">16 In what place of the Scripture, power is giuen to the <hi>Pope,</hi> to gather into the treaſury of the Church, the ſuper-aboundant ſatisfactions of Saints, and of Monkes, and to conuert them into payment for others, diſtributing them by Indulgences.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Laſtly, where and when hath God giuen power to the <hi>Pope</hi> to depoſe Kings, to draw ſoules out of Purgatorie, and to giue pardons for ſeauen or eight hundred thouſand yeares.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe ſeauenteene poynts, which make the Body of Popery, and wherein the abuſe and tyranny thereof conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, we aske Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> whether he will produce any places of holy Scripture to proue them, and wee will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with one place onely for euery ſeuerall poynt. Our meaning is not to reſtraine him to finde theſe things in the Scripture word by word, it ſhall ſuffice vs, if he can finde them there in ſubſtance, or that they can be deduced by good conſequence. For we ſeeke no delayes, nor are not ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the number of ſyllables, ſo the thing be proued in the word of God. Now we muſt ſee what anſwere M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> maketh to theſe queſtions, and how he proueth his Religion by the Word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:11469:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> anſwere to theſe Queſtions.</head>
               <p>THe Aduerſarie maketh anſwere in theſe words.<note place="margin">1. 100. page of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> Booke.</note> Firſt (he ſaith) it belongeth not vnto them to aske me the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my beleefe, becauſe I am in poſſeſſion, &amp; no man hath giuen them commiſſion to pull the title of the inheritance which I hold, out of my hands.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that it is true, that we haue no power to make him ſpeake, nor to binde him to giue vs an anſwere; but the commandement of God bindeth him thereunto, in the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>S. Peter</hi> 3.15. <hi>Be ready alwayes to giue an anſwere to euery man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekeneſſe and feare.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt made anſwere touching his doctrine to thoſe that came vnto him, although they were his enemles, and had no power ouer him: We haue anſwered M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> to all whatſoeuer he demanded of vs, and obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt vs, although he hath no power ouer vs, neither did ſhew vs his commiſſion. He hath bound himſelfe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vs, becauſe he prouoked vs to ſpeake. For, that asking vs a reaſon of our religion, he might make his account that we would aske him a reaſon of his religion: not in manner of reuenge, but to let the truth be knowne, and to ſhew that wee are better grounded in Religion then he is.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſaith, that he is in poſſeſſion of an inheritance, and that we haue no commiſſion to take it from him; If by that inheritance he vnderſtandeth earthly poſſeſſions, and riches, we enuie him not, and wiſh that he had ten times as much more, ſo he would become a defender of the truth: But if by that inheritance, hee vnderſtandeth the poſſeſſion of the true doctrine, it is to preſuppoſe that which is in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. We goe not about to take a thing from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſhe hath partly loſt. There needs no commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to aske a man what he beleeueth, or the reaſon of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. Charitie towards all men, and a deſire to lend our hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand to him that is fallen, and the zeale that we ought
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11469:6"/> to beare to the defence of Gods cauſe, ſufficiently bindeth vs to ſpeake, and to propound the doctrine of ſaluation to thoſe that require it. It is to no purpoſe to ſay; it is already long time ſince I haue bin in poſſeſſion of this doctrine: For Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Iewes, and Turkes may ſay as much, whoſe religions are ancienter then Papiſtry. We diſpute not by numbers or yeeres, but by proofes. The Church is in a Country where there is a written Law, and not in a Country where cuſtome onely ruleth. There is no preſcription againſt the heauenly truth, which alwayes is moſt ancient, for that vntruth or lying is but a corruption of the truth. An ancient opinion once was new: and if time may authorize a doctrine, tell me how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres at the leaſt, me muſt haue to giue authoritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto? Then we muſt proceed to the ground, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution contained in the Word of God. And without ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Word of God, yet it will be found, that the moſt part of the errors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are very new. As the depoſing of Kings by the Pope, the Communion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one kinde, The forbidding to reade the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2 M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> addeth and ſaith, Their requeſt ſhould be more tollerable, if they made it before ſome Iudge that had authoritie to end our difference.</p>
               <p>If this excuſe, made by the Ieſuite, were allowable, before he ſets vpon vs he ought to finde out a Iudge that could ſet vs at an agreement. But that notwithſtanding, we haue not ſpared to anſwere him, becauſe, that although at this day there is no man to be found that is fit to be a Iudge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, with infallible certainty, and ſoueraigne authority; yet euery particular man ought to haue iudgement with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, to diſcerne which of vs beſt proueth and iuſtifieth his ſayings by the Word of God. Then that ſhould bee no hinderance vnto him to anſwere vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The third excuſe that he addeth, is no better then the former: which is; ſeeing (ſaith he) that they haue bound themſelues to re-eſtabliſh the Church that is fallen, and that I offer my ſelfe vnto them, to be drawne out of the ruines,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11469:6"/> wherewith (as they thinke) I am incloſed. It belongs to them to lend me their hand, to ſhew me thoſe notable places, and to produce the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, that it is falſe that we haue taken vpon vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Church, and that wee haue bound our ſelues thereunto. It is ſufficient for vs to reforme our ſelues. They call our Churches reformed, and not reformers. And they are called reformed, becauſe they are Chriſtian Churches purged from Papiſtrie. It is true, that as euery true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is moued with compaſſion towards thoſe that erre; we could gladly wiſh that our aduerſaries eyes were opened, and that we could take the vaile of ignorance from before them. But yet we take not on vs the title of reformers. I am perſwaded that our aduerſaries which beleeue that they haue the truth on their ſides, would be glad if they could doe the like for vs: and yet not aſcribe the title of Reformators vnto themſelues. And although we ſhould call our ſelues refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, is it not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> dutie to ſhew vs, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be reformed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by prouing his beleefe by the Word of God; thereby to withdraw vs from this vnprofitable labour, and to hinder vs from applying any more plaſters, where there is no wound? Then that likewiſe ſhould not hinder him from anſwering vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That which followeth is no better; vntill (ſaith he) that they haue confuted my Paper of confrontation, againſt the which they haue written, it were a kind of folly in mee, to grant them ſuch a diſloyall and friuolous digreſſion.</p>
               <p>For anſwere hereunto, I ſay, that we haue in ſuch manner confuted his confrontations, that they are become ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. His accuſations did not merit the paines were tooke therein, but we had a reſpect to the dignitie of the perſons, in whoſe preſence he pronounced them. And when any man moueth vs to render a reaſon of our beleefe, it is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, to cauſe him to yeeld a reaſon of his owne beleefe. For a man alwayes to aske queſtions, and neuer to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to any thing that another askes him, beſides the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt vſurpation, it is a confeſſion of his owne Ignorance. For
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11469:7"/> he that askes, deſireth to be inſtructed, and hee that will not anſwere, ſilently confeſſeth that he is not able to giue inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And if when we make theſe queſtions vnto him, we ſhould vſe a digreſſion, yet ſeeing that our people are not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and becauſe we cannot ſatisfie their demaunds by the Word of God, it is M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noux</hi> part to ſupply their want therein, and to giue them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; Seeing that if his cauſe be good, he ſhall haue leſſe paines to produce a place out of the Scripture touching eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of our 17. demaunds, then to ſeeke for ſo many ſhifts; He takes more paines to ſhew the reaſons why he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth not, then he ſhould haue had to anſwere vs.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The fift reaſon is excellent. When (ſaith he) they ſhall plainly and freely confeſſe, that they can no more brag and boaſt of the Word of God, and that their confeſſion is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboliſhed, and that it is no more to be ſpoken of: Then I will make no difficultie to inſtruct them in my beleefe, and it ſhall not be to the end to make them account thereof, but to winne them to God.</p>
               <p>He will haue me to leaue my owne Religion before he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs me in his beleefe, but in the meane time what Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall I hold while I attend his inſtruction? This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent counſell, to wiſh me to leaue my Religion without taking another in a certaine time after, and that I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce my confeſſion of the faith, before I know whether he that induceth me to doe it, hath a good religion: And if after I haue left my Religion, without taking another; I come to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> to learne his faith of him, and that therein hee doth not content me, ſhall I remaine without Religion, or ſhall I take that againe which I left? That is as much as if a man ſhould leaue his owne Religion, not knowing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: For I cannot know that my Religion is falſe, vnleſſe I know that the contrary Religion is true. This Doctor hath learned all this from Father <hi>Gontri,</hi> that publiſhed diuers ſmall Treaties, wherein are found theſe ſlender ſhifts and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh conceipts, to learne men to exempt themſelues from anſwering, alwayes to aske queſtions, and to bind vs to proue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11469:7"/> our allegations in as many words and ſyllables out of the holy Scripture.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Laſtly, after ſo many ouerthwartings, Truth giueth M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> a blow, and draweth this confeſſion from him. Such queſtions (ſaith hee) cannot be made by thoſe that know well, that we neuer promiſed, as they haue done, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet proteſted in any of our Articles, that we ought not to beleeue any thing, but that which is formerly ſet downe in the Scripture, and in expreſſe termes: to the contrary wee hold traditions, which they reproue and reiect.</p>
               <p>He ſhould haue ſaid ſo at the firſt, without ſeeking ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ouerthwartings and delayes. Then he confeſſeth that he cannot anſwer our queſtions by the Scripture, and that thoſe points whereof we deſire a proofe, are not proued by the Word of God, contained in the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, but by tradition, and by the vnwritten Word; That is to ſay, that theſe doctrines are neither in the Law of God, nor in the Goſpell; for in the holy Scriptures the Law of God is whole, and the Goſpell whole, and not halfe, vnleſſe the title be falſe, And yet theſe 17. points, are the principall points of the Romiſh Religion, and which are held to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſaluation, &amp; which are the cauſes of our ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then be it knowne to all the Realme of <hi>France,</hi> that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux,</hi> being at this day ſeated in ſo eminent a place, (after hee hath defied vs with ſo ſolemne a defiance in the preſence of his Maieſtie, and of the greateſt perſons of this Realme,) hath bled at the noſe, &amp; confeſſeth his own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and acknowledgeth that his Religion is not grounded vpon the Word of God, contained in the holy Scriptures, but vpon an vnwritten Word, and vpon Traditions, which haue no other rule, nor certainty, then the authority of thoſe that propound them: and who by that tradition haue heaped vp infinite riches, and builded an Empire vpon earth. While the holy Scriptures which is <hi>able to make vs wiſe to ſaluation;</hi> is hidden, and withdrawne from the peoples ſight. And that we on the contrary haue from point to point ſatisfied and anſwered to all his queſtions and obiections. Bleſſed bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11469:8"/> the Name of God, that makes truth to triumph, and drawes our aduerſaries condemnation out of their owne mouthes. Then with good reaſon he addeth theſe words; ſaying, they did well to conceiue that I would neuer vndertake an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent thing: and that alſo which hee ſaith, that wee would haue him loſe dayes and nights, and ſpoile his breſt, and his ſtomacke with ſo much writing, and abandon his charge, and then ſtay a long time for an anſwere, and ſtriking after one manner, he ſhould loſe his blowes. It is not impertinent to defend his cauſe by the word of God, that paines will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurt nor ſpoile his breſt nor ſtomacke; For, it is ſo hard a matter, to produce a place out of the Scriptures for euery one of theſe 17. points, and if not formall, at the leaſt, ſuch as haue ſome appearance thereof.</p>
               <p>Touching the places of the Scripture alleadged by Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. and by the laſt Counſell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> in ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious and prophane a ſenſe; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arnoux p. <hi>112.</hi>
                  </note> dares not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch cotations of the Scripture, nor yet reiect them, leaſt hee ſhould condemne the Popes and their Counſels, but findes a way betweene both, ſaying, That thoſe proofes are not produced in the literall ſenſe, but in an accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and appropriated ſenſe, nothing contrary to the literall ſenſe. I will make our greateſt enemies Iudges herein, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would endure that in our confeſſion wee ſhould ſerue our ſelues with places of Scripture not agreeing with the literall ſenſe, but with an accommodated ſenſe, made for our pleaſures, and drawne for our profit, for thoſe places are interpreted for the Popes aduantage, in an impious ſenſe, to perſwade men, that he ought to be adored by Kings, and that he hath all power in heauen and in earth. Are theſe the men that will binde vs, to finde all that in the Scripture which we ſay, and in as many words and ſyllables, who in the meane time, take libertie themſelues to play with the Scripture with ſuch licentious prophanation, and thinke to carry it away by ſaying that it is an accommodated and not a literall ſenſe, which accommodated ſenſe neuertheleſſe, they receiue for good and moſt certaine, ſeeing they hold that the Pope and his Counſels cannot erre in faith?</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11469:8"/>
               <p>After this Doctor hath ſo barely acquitted himſelfe, hee ſpeaketh as being touched with compaſſion towards vs, and giueth vs counſell full of wiſedome, ſaying, Yeeld your ſelues to the Church, and ſhe will tell you all: as if he ſhould ſay, Ioyne your ſelues with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and then wee will at leaſure anſwere to your demands: for by the Church he vnderſtandeth the Romiſh Church, which he will haue vs to beleeue to be the true Church, before we know what ſhee ought to beleeue, that ſhee may be the true and pure Church. But why ſhould ſhee rather be the true Church than the Greeke or the Syrian Churches, which are ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the Romane, and purer, and which Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles did plant, and where S. <hi>Peters</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles chaires are?</p>
               <p>Thereupon Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> will haue vs plainely to ſhew which is the true Church, if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be not the true Church; but he ſaith that to mocke vs: for he ſpeaketh as if he ſhould ſay, Shew vs that, but while you ſhew it, wee will ſhut our eyes: for the true Church is that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth and teacheth the true Doctrine contained in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, by that we muſt know it, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccleſiae, cap. <hi>16.</hi> Vtrum ipſi Eccleſiam teneant non niſi diuinaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis libris oſtenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Et eodem libro. Ergo in Canonicis Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis eam requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus. Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> let vs ſeeke for the Church in the canonicall Scriptures: <hi>that is,</hi> that holy Scripture which they hide from the people. Then theſe Doctors will haue vs to ſhew them the true Church, but will not haue men to ſee that, which onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them to know the Church. As if a man would haue one to ſhew him the beſt gouerned Common-wealth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing the rules that make a good Common-wealth. He alſo will haue vs to produce our Commiſſion, and the charge that we haue from that Church. Whereunto we haue anſwered in the 123. Section of the firſt Booke, where wee haue handled the vocation of Paſtors. The effect thereof is, that although euery Paſtor of our Churches be lawfully called, and according to the forme and manner therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, by impoſition of the hands of other faithfull Paſtors, after enquiry made of his life and conuerſation, and of his capacity and doctrine, yet it is not alwaies neceſſary to haue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11469:9"/> his commiſsion, and allowance from a pure Church, and without errour. He that is admitted into the charge of a Paſtor, in an hereticall Church, (as in an Arian or Neſtorian Church) and that hath beene receiued vpon oath to teach the truth, ought neceſſarily to accompliſh that oath, and in the ſame charge to change his hereticall doctrine, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the true Doctrine of ſaluation: Not only becauſe the charge of a Paſtor, in what Church ſoeuer it be, by the nature thereof, and the firſt inſtitution, is expreſly giuen vnto him, and inſtituted to teach the truth, but alſo becauſe that euery oath made to God concerning any good, iuſt, and neceſſary thing, and whereinto a man hath not intruded himſelfe, ought neceſſarily to be accompliſhed. And if it hapneth, that any Paſtors of an hereticall and an idolatrous Church, as the Romiſh Church is, changing their hereticall doctrine, and taking on them to preach the truth, and thereby draw a part of their flockes to follow the truth, and that thereupon the other part, obſtinate in errour, expulſeth and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them, I ſay that they ought to be conſtant, and not to abandon Gods cauſe, &amp; that they may not leaue their charge, for accompliſhing their oathes, but conuert their charge into the true vſe thereof: for they ought rather to haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Gods will and intent, for the which hee hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the charge of Paſtors, than to the intent of thoſe that impoſed their hands vpon them, when it is contrary to Gods will and intent: for a man is not eſtabliſhed in the charge of a Paſtor to doe the will of man, but the will of God: The force of the bond to obſerue and keepe his oath, proceedeth not from him before whom he taketh his oath, or that maketh him to ſweare, but from God to whom hee ſweareth, and in whoſe power the puniſhments of periury are reſerued. Such was the commiſſion and the proceedings of thoſe whom God vſed to ſtriue againſt Papiſtrie in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and openly to publiſh the holy Scripture, which the Pope had ſuppreſſed, who hauing beene choſen and elected Prieſts and Doctors in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to preach the Doctrine of the Goſpel to the people, and to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11469:9"/> ſacrificers of the body of Chriſt, did beleeue that they were bound to performe the firſt, becauſe it is the ordinance of God, and to leaue the ſecond, becauſe it is the inuention of man. Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> addeth a conceipt, which hee ſaith is very ſtrong, and of much force, the ſubſtance whereof is, That no Teſtament is made without there be an heire; That the Teſtament is the Goſpel; That the Church is the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall aſſigned heire of this Teſtament, the which by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence cannot erre, as being perpetuall inheritor of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible truth. I anſwere, that the inheritance which Ieſus Chriſt by his teſtament hath left to the true faithfull,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.14.18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.15.</note> is the Kingdome of Heauen, and not the guift, not to erre. And although the infallible truth of God might be called the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Church, yet it doth not follow that the Church cannot erre, nor ſinne againſt the truth. So the law, which is the intire rule of righteouſneſſe, is giuen to the Church, which neuertheleſſe doth ſinne againſt that Law. How ſhould the Vniuerſall Church be without error, ſeeing it is compoſed of diuers and particular diſcordant Churches? among the which, why ſhould the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> rather haue the guift not to erre, than the <hi>Greeke,</hi> ancienter than the <hi>Romane,</hi> or than the <hi>Syrrian,</hi> much ancienter than the <hi>Greeke,</hi> and where Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chaire is, and which Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe planted? as alſo, ſeeing that the reſt of the Apoſtles hauing left no ſucceſſors in their Apoſtles charge, why ſhould Saint <hi>Peter</hi> onely haue one in his? Did Ieſus Chriſt euer declare that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> onely, among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſhould haue a ſucceſſor in his charge of Apoſtle? or did Saint <hi>Peter</hi> euer declare that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be his ſucceſſour in quality of the head of the vniuerſall Church? Where is there any one word of this ſucceſſion vſed in the Word of God? As alſo that the hereſies<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo</hi> the ſecond complaineth of <hi>Honorius</hi> his Predeceſſor, for that by his hereſie he had defiled the ſeat of <hi>Rome.</hi> In the action 18. of the 6. Councell.</note> of diuers <hi>Popes,</hi> (acknowledged by the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelues,) and the ſchiſmes which haue rent that Seate, and which often times haue bin the meanes, that of diuers <hi>Antipopes</hi> contending for the ſame, the wickedeſt and the moſt vniuſt of them intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe, hath carried it away: haue partly broken the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11469:10"/> line of this imaginary ſucceſſion: for to what purpoſe doth it ſerue to ſhew a liſt of mens names in a picture, from Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to our time, if they ſhew not that the ſecond of them taught as the firſt did, and the third as the ſecond, and ſo by degrees? Many hereticall Churches in that manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their ſucceſsion, and are nothing the better for that; for a ſucceſsion of a chaire, without ſucceſsion of Doctrine, is rather an expulſion than a ſucceſsion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>120.</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nius lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>But M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſaith, that learned <hi>Irenius</hi> ſaith, that it is altogether neceſſary that euery Church ſhould reſort and ioyne vnto that of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein the chiefe Principalitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. But M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter <hi>Arnoux,</hi> hauing not in all his Booke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place that is not either cut ſhort or falſified, would not at the end of his booke begin to alledge them truely. For, firſt he addeth this word <hi>adherer,</hi> which is not in <hi>Ireni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the word <hi>conuenire</hi> he tranſlateth <hi>reſorting,</hi> whereas it ſignifieth to land, or to come from diuers places into one place. And to theſe two falſhoods, Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> addeth a notable corruption of the ſenſe; for <hi>Irenius</hi> by this chiefe Principalitie, vnderſtandeth the power of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe of the emperiall Seate, and not of the ſupremacie of the Biſhop, or of his Church; for that, Chriſtians from all Churches, arriued at, or came to <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Seate, and of the Senate, where they had ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires to be diſpatched: As if I ſhould ſay, that from all the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> they come to <hi>Paris,</hi> becauſe the Kings ſoueraigne Court is there. Then we muſt tranſlate <hi>Irenius</hi> in this mannner: To this Church<note n="*" place="margin">Ad hanc Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, propter potentiam pr n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atem, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt omnem co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> all Churches muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily come, becauſe of the ſoueraigne power, which is the emperiall power. Vpon the ſame reaſon, the councell of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> in the ninth Canon, groundeth the ſuperioritie of the Biſhops of great Townes, becauſe (ſaith that Councell) that all thoſe that haue any buſineſſe, come to the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane City; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or that cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it hath beene ordained that the Biſhops thereof ſhould haue preheminence of honour. Therefore the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> went before <hi>Antiochia,</hi> although the Church of <hi>Antiochia</hi> was ancienter, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11469:10"/> (as it is ſaid) by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe that among the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Romiſh Empire, <hi>Alexandria,</hi> according to ciuill order, was the ſecond City after <hi>Rome,</hi> and was before <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia.</hi> The 17. Canon of the Councell of <hi>Calcidonia,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expreſly thereof; where it is ordained, that the order of Eccleſiaſticall Dioces ſhould be accommodated according to ciuill and publique forme.</p>
               <p>For concluſion, our aduerſary immitating (as he ſaith) the example of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> referreth vs to the Fathers, that are not partiall in this cauſe.</p>
               <p>I maruell why hee doth not rather referre vs to the Word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is not partiall, no more than the ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are, and which ſpeaketh with another manner of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and much more, that he referreth the people to the reading of the Greeke and Latine Fathers, whoſe workes are infinite to be read, and the vnderſtanding of them obſcure, and, which hee knoweth, the common people vnderſtand not, and that out of their workes, there are not many places alledged, whereupon there is not ſome queſtion made touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſenſe and the interpretation of them. And I am much more abaſht that he referreth the people to the reading of the Fathers, to be reſolued in Religion, ſeeing there is not one of the Fathers, which the Doctors of the Romiſh Church doe not cenſure, and often times reproue them: For they make themſelues Iudges of the Fathers, in ſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the Fathers for Iudges. In their bookes of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies you ſhall ſee nothing but diuers opinions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wherof they chooſe thoſe whom they pleaſe and reiect the reſt, and many times reiect them all, to eſtabliſh their owne opinions.</p>
               <p>Now to ſhew, that the reaſon why they referre the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people to the reading of the Fathers, is not becauſe the Fathers fauour them, but onely to ſhun the holy Scriptures, which they feare, and to leade the mindes of the common-people through a way wherein they can neither ſee nor know any thing: I would gladly know, whether our aduerſaries receiue the Fathers for Iudges in all our Controuerſies; if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11469:11"/> they receiued them not for Iudges but in certain poynts, why not alſo in others? but if they receiue them for Iudges in all things, then they muſt enter into the liſts, and let ſome of them ſhew vs in the Fathers, theſe ſeauenteene poynts, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, hauing beene ſo often times preſt and vrged, they are yet to anſwere.</p>
               <p n="1">1 For I ſay, and maintaine it, that they cannot ſhew that any ancient Church euer celebrated the Euchariſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out communicants, as they ordinarily doe in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and many times alſo without any aſſiſtants.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They cannot ſhew, that any ancient Church kept the people from the communion of the cup.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Or that in any ancient Church, publique Seruice, and the reading of the holy Scriptures, was done in a language not vnderſtood by the people.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Or that any ancient Church, did forbid or hinder the people from reading of the holy Scripture, which is by no meanes permitted without ſpeciall priuiledge in theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where the Pope is abſolutely obayed.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Or that in any ancient Church, they made Images of God, and repreſentation of the Trinity, in ſtone or in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Neither can they ſhew vs, that in any ancient Church the people haue been taught to pray without vnderſtanding what they ſay, and to be Barbarians to themſelues.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Or that any ancient Church, hath done any ſeruice to the Images of creatures, as kiſſing, clothing, kneeling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, or offering vnto them.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Or that the ancient Church did beleeue that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is crowned Queene of Heauen, and Lady of the World, as ſhe is painted in all the Papiſts Churches.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Or that the ancient Church gaue diuers charges and offices to Saints, to one ouer one Country, to another ouer another Countrey, to another ouer an occupation, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Or that the ancient Church beleeued that the <hi>Pope</hi> can giue, and take away Kingdomes, and diſpence with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects touching their oath of fidelity, cannonize Saints, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11469:11"/> diſpence with vowes and oathes made to God.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Or that in the ancient Church, the Pope by his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, diſtributed the ſupererogatory ſatisfactions of Saints, for remiſſion of the puniſhments for other mens ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="12">12 Or that the Pope then, ſet vp pardons in one Church &amp; not in another, making priuiledged Alters, to the which ſometimes hee granted two or three hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres of pardon.</p>
               <p n="13">13 Or that the ancient Church did beleeue that there is a place called <hi>Limbus</hi> for yong children.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Or that it adored the hoſte which the Prieſt holdeth in his hands, with <hi>Latrian</hi> worſhip, and that to the ſame end the Prieſt lifteth vp the hoſte in the Maſſe.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Or that the ancient Church euer eſteemed the books of <hi>Machabees</hi> to be Canonicall bookes.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Or that it beleeued that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot erre in the faith.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Or that the ancient Church did beleeue that Ieſus Chriſt by his death and paſſion did ſatisfie for the faults and for the ſinnes by men committed before baptiſme, but that for ſinnes committed after baptiſme it belongeth to vs to ſatisfie for them, either in this life, or in the fire of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
               <p>Vpon euery one of theſe points, I will content my ſelfe with two places alleadged by them out of the foure firſt ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The fiue manners or wayes of Euaſions, ſet downe by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> to confute the Miniſters.</head>
               <p>THe carefull and zealous reading of the holy Scriptures; and the ancient doctors; the vnderſtanding of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, Greeke, and Hebrew tongues, and the knowledge of hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and of Philoſophie, are things required to be in a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. But the onely intelligence of the Scriptures ought to ſuffice if all of vs were wiſe, and of one accord; But the ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11469:12"/> of this age, and the ſtarting-holes which error hath dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, are the cauſes that diuers other things are required in a Diuine. Father <hi>Gontri</hi> deceaſed, acknowledging that, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe to be deſtitute of many neceſſary aides therin, as of the knowledge of the Greek &amp; Hebrew tongues, &amp; yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to win reputation, inuented certaine means and wayes whereby an ignorant perſon, voide of all learning, might maintaine a diſputation, and to that end publiſhed diuers ſmal Pamphlets, which ſerue to forme and frame the manner and order which thoſe that diſpute or conferre with vs, ſhould hold, to whom he giueth theſe two counſels: The firſt is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to yeeld to make any anſwere, nor to binde themſelues to defend the Romiſh Religion, but alwayes to put queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to force vs to the defence of our confeſſion. And if they be preſſed to proue their beleefe by the Word of God, inſtead of anſwering vs, that they ſhould ſay, It belongs not to you to examine me of my beleefe, for I am in poſſeſſion, and you haue no commiſſion to examine me; Seeing you are reformers, it belongs to you to reforme mee, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your proofes. And, who told you that this is the holy Scripture?</p>
               <p>The other counſell which hee giueth is, that when wee come to make obiections, and to produce our proofes, not to allow of any thing whatſoeuer we ſhall ſay, if wee ſhew it not in the Scripture in as many words and ſyllables as wee alledge it; and that, if we frame an argument whereof both the propoſitions are in the Scriptures, to deny that they are bound to allow the concluſion, becauſe <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> rules doe not binde the faith: And that, if in our diſcourſe we ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to vſe theſe words. <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> or, <hi>by conſequence,</hi> they ſhould force vs to finde thoſe words, <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> and, <hi>by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence</hi> in the Scripture: And that if we produce a place in the Scripture for the clearing and interpretation of another place in the Scripture, they ſhould ſay vnto vs, ſhew mee a third place in the Scripture, which ſaith, that this place ought to be expounded by that place: And that, if we doe not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them to their deſires, then that they ſhall breake off
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11469:12"/> conference, and thereupon make and raiſe clamors and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous libels, full of triumphant words, that they haue brought the Miniſters to their Shifts of <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> and, <hi>by conſequences,</hi> and to ſay that a Caroach alſo is a conſequence, becauſe it followeth the horſes.</p>
               <p>There is no Cobler in the Countrey, but that in a quarter of an houre he may become a Diuine, if it be ſufficient al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to put queſtions, and neuer to anſwere. Certainely all this is but a ſmall <hi>maſſe or lumpe</hi> of ſcould-like wrangling, which onely learneth a man to defend himſelfe with his clawes like a Cat, and to prolong a diſputation, neuer entring into the matter. But this dreſſer of craftineſſe and deceit, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reaped any benefit by his proceedings; for at the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the leaſt of the Miniſters, his noſe fell a blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and all his craft vaniſhed away, like a tempeſt driuen backe with the winde of a Hatte, and ſo withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a <hi>light horſeman</hi> vnhorſt, went into another towne, there to be dealt withall in the like manner.</p>
               <p>If we would giue the like meaſure to thoſe that vſe theſe iugling trickes, we could at the firſt word that they ſpeake, aske them, who they are, and who ſent them, and vpon their anſwere, that they are Prieſts and Doctors of the Church, ſay vnto them, what know wee whether there muſt bee a Church or not, or that there is a Church? and thereupon if they ſpeake any thing, ſay vnto them, ſhew that in as many words in the written or vnwritten word. And if they chance to come out with <hi>Therefore,</hi> or, <hi>for that cauſe,</hi> ſay vnto them, ſhew me that word in the vnwritten word, and who ſhall be Iudge? &amp;c. And ſo like them vſe that ſimple wrangling which is fit onely for mad-men and malitious wranglers, that feare the touch, and dare not ſhew their faces in open field.</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> followeth this inſtruction, fit for a man that is meanely furniſhed, and decking himſelfe with other birds feathers, hath drawne theſe ſubtilties into a kinde of Art, and reduced them into fiue heads, intitling his diſcourſe, <hi>Meanes,</hi> or, <hi>wayes of euaſion;</hi> Wherevnder pretence to diſcouer our ſhifts, as they ſay, hee ſheweth his owne, and frames
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11469:13"/> a diſcipline of ſmall and ſlender ſubtilties, fitter rather to ſtay and hinder diſputation, then to inſtruct. To each of theſe Euaſions, we will ſay ſomewhat, that we may not let any thing paſſe without replying.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The firſt way of Euaſion.</head>
               <p>THe firſt of our wiles which he noteth, is, that when we are put from a place of Scripture, we produce our own inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, and ſaue our credits by, <hi>That is to ſay.</hi> Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I reply, That if the interpretation which we giue to a place in the Scripture, be drawne out of the Scripture it ſelfe, it is not we that are the interpreters, but God himſelfe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: For example, when to haue the vnderſtanding of theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> wee expound the word <hi>This,</hi> by the bread which I breake, and theſe words, <hi>my Body,</hi> by <hi>the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of my Body,</hi> we are not the interpreters, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, which giue vs this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</p>
               <p>So when the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 13.16. ſaith <hi>for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed;</hi> We deny that thoſe ſacrifices whereof he ſpeaketh are maſſes, and ſay, that he ſpeaketh of doing good and of Chriſtian liberalitie, and proue it by the ſame verſe, where he ſaith, <hi>But to doe good, and to communicate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> But, in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> iudgement ſuch expoſitions are not allowable, if I bring him not another place of Scripture that ſaith, that the ſame interpretation is true, and that this place ought to be expounded by that place. So, it is requiſite that ſome of the bookes of the Scripture ſhould be commentaries vpon the other bookes, and that in the Scripture there ſhould be a Commentary vpon the Pſalmes, and another vpon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that ſhould expound euery verſe ſeuerally, and that ſhould ſay, that ſuch and ſuch a verſe ought thus to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted: but ſeeing there are no ſuch Commentaries in the Scriptures, it appeareth that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> hath no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11469:13"/> but to inquire abſurd and impoſſible things of vs, and ſo neuer to haue the Scripture to be interpreted by the Scripture, and thereby to impeach and hinder all inſtruction. For example, of our, <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> produceth the 2. verſe of the 16. Pſalme, where word for word according to the Hebrew. It is, <hi>My goodneſſe extendeth not to thee:</hi> And wee ſay that thereby <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledgeth that the good which he doth is no benefit vnto God, and that God hath no need thereof, which ouerthroweth merits. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth this interpretation, (which notwithſtanding is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of his owne Bible) which is tranſlated, <hi>Bonorum meorum non eges,</hi> thou haſt no need of my good deeds. This man with a blinde zeale giueth a blow to euery thing, and to contradict vs, contradicteth himſelfe.</p>
               <p>That which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> addeth, that euery one of vs boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of a particular Spirit, and of a Iudgement <hi>ſounder</hi> then that of the vniuerſall Church is a ſlander, none of vs attribute ſuch a ſpirit vnto our ſelues, ſuch a particular ſpirit is an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The ſecond Euaſion.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond Euaſion, wherewith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſaith wee ſerue our turnes, is, that we haue our recourſe to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, which (ſaith he) we would not doe if we had a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall place of Scripture: And that to confirme our conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, we make Sillogiſmes, the formes whereof proceede from <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> forge, which cannot binde mens conſciences, nor ſtrengthen faith. All this is the Ieſuite <hi>Gonters</hi> fenſe, which alwaies held his firſt trade. He knew not that a place of Scripture from whence we draw a conſequence, is neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe formall, when the conſequence is plaine and neceſſary. If the Scripture ſaith, <hi>For there is no man which ſinneth not,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.36. Is not that a formall place to prooue that the Apoſtles ſinned, ſeeing they were men? When the Law of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11469:14"/> God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie,</hi> Is it not a formall place to ſhew that the Pope doth euill to permit adulterie, and yet it followeth by conſequence? And when the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell commandeth euery man to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, is not that a formall place to prooue that <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Anthony</hi> ought to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, and yet that followeth by conſequence? So when S. <hi>Paul Romans</hi> 9.19. ſaith, <hi>For who hath reſiſted his will?</hi> And when <hi>Dauid Pſal.</hi> 115.3. ſaith, <hi>But our God is in the Heauens, he hath done whatſoeuer hee pleaſed;</hi> Are not theſe formall places to prooue that God guideth all things by his prouidence? Neuertheleſſe, the Ieſuites, will not allow of ſuch proofes, and when I ſay, that God guideth all things by his prouidence, they ſay vnto me, prooue that by the Scripture, and then if I alledge theſe places out of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> they reiect them, becauſe they containe not the ſame words, and the ſame ſyllables, but conſequences drawne from them by reaſon.<note place="margin">Acts 17.3. and 18.28.</note> By this meanes they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> who by the Scriptures prooued to the Iewes, that Ieſus is that Chriſt, although that in thoſe places of the Scripture which they alledged to the Iewes, the ſame words are not therein found, but are drawne from them by neceſſary conſequence. So S. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 10.43. ſaith. <hi>To him giue all the Prophets witneſſe, that through his Name, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhall receiue remiſſion of ſinnes.</hi> Which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe is not found in the ſame words, but is drawne from thence by conſequence. So the Fathers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Nice,</hi> by the Scriptures proue, that the Son is conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall with the father, and the firſt Counſell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Deipara,</hi> Theſe words are not expreſly found there, but are drawne from them by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory de Nazianze,</hi> in his fift Oration of Diuinitie, ſaith; There are things which although they are not named in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words, yet men gather things which make and prooue them by neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>Cardinall <hi>Iohn de Turre Cremata</hi> ſaith, A thing is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11469:14"/> in the Scripture by theſe two meanes,<note place="margin">Summa de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> either in expreſſe word, as in this ſentence, Chriſt was a man or obſcurely, that is, that which followeth by good and neceſſary conſequence of things formally placed on earth; as from this propoſition, Chriſt was a man, therefore it followeth that he had a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter de Alliaco,</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Cambray,</hi> ſaith, I ſay,<note place="margin">In <hi>1.</hi> Sentent. Queſt. <hi>1.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> that to ſpeake properly, a Theologicall diſcourſe is compoſed of propoſitions contained in the Scripture, or of thoſe that are drawne from it, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his third Booke of Iuſtification, Cap. 8. ſaith, Nothing can be certaine touching the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of faith; if it be not immediately contained in the Word of God, or drawne from thence by euident and true conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. For it is not faith, if it be not grounded vpon the authority of the Word of God, and thereof neither Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes nor Heretiques make any doubt. Then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux,</hi> which doubteth thereof, by the iudgement of a Cardinall and a Ieſuite, is no Catholique.</p>
               <p>Where as hee ſaith, that hee would haue no Sillogiſmes allowed of; there is a meanes to content him, by ſpeaking with him as with children, ſeeing hee reiecteth the naturall rules of reaſon: which are not <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> inuention, as he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, <hi>Zeno Eleates</hi> and diuers others before him wrote of that matter.<note n="a" place="margin">Diog. Laerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Zenone Eleate. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Plaine Countrey people vſe thoſe rules, not thinking thereon, being inſenſibly thruſt into them by the force of reaſon. Whoſoeuer will haue no conſequences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, aboliſheth all common ſenſe, and all vſe of reaſon, which onely conſiſteth therein. The rules of Lodgique are no Articles of faith, but inſtruments to mannage all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by order and certainty, and by conſequence alſo, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Diuinitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:11469:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The third Euaſion.</head>
               <p>THe third Euaſion which Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſaith we vſe, is, that we ſerue our turnes with the circle; in this, that we proue thoſe things to be Scripture by our particular ſpirit, and proue that particular ſpirit by the Scripture. Which is falſe and ſlanderous. We leaue that particular ſpirit to mad men, none of vs makes our ſelues Iudges of the Scriptures; That is the Popes and his Prelates property, who being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled boaſt that they pronounce Iudgement touching points of faith, and beleeue they cannot erre. And our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſay, that euery particular perſon of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth certainly diſcerne the true Church, which ſpirit or particular iudgement, is meere blindneſſe, ſeeing that the poore people haue no other proofe to know that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the true Church, then onely the witneſſe that the ſame Church giueth of itſelfe.</p>
               <p>Touching the circle, if any ſerue their turnes therewith, it is our aduerſaries, for they ground the authoritie of the Scripture vpon the teſtimony of the Church: and yet ground the authoritie of the Church vpon teſtimonies of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: as one that hauing placed the walles of a houſe vpon the foundation, afterward ſhould place the foundation vpon the walles. When we aske them, how they know that wee muſt beleeue the bookes of the new Teſtament; They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſay, becauſe the Church ſaith it, and ordaines it to be ſo: and when we ſay, that how know you that wee muſt beleeue the Church? becauſe (ſay they) that the bookes of the New Teſtament ſay ſo, and ordaine it to be ſo, for there it is written, <hi>Tell it vnto the Church, &amp;c.</hi> Certainely as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they alledge the Scriptures to ground and authorize their Church, they ouerthrow that which they will haue men to beleeue; which is, that the authority of the Scripture
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11469:15"/> is grounded vpon the authority of the Church. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are tyed to rowle the circle, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> is to his tub, and ouerturne their owne wits by this circulation. But when we aske one of them, and ſay, how know you that your Church teacheth the true Doctrine? or how know you that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the ancient Church? There they are at a ſtay, and the circle rowles no more, and ſo they are dumbe by neceſſity: For how ſhall they know the true Doctrine, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rule of the true Doctrine, which is the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is hidden from them? And how ſhould they know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Church is conformable to the ancient Church, ſeeing it is not knowne, but by an infinite number of Greeke and Latine Bookes, which the people vnderſtand not? Then the people muſt know that the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome teacheth the true Doctrine, onely becauſe thoſe that teach it, ſay ſo, which is to belieue at hazard, and to haue a humane Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, grounded vpon coniectures, without the Word of God, and to allow a man to be a witneſſe and a Iudge in his owne cauſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> giueth markes to know the true Church, without ſpeaking of the holy Scriptures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 119.</note> which are all falſe. Firſt, <hi>The conſent of the people.</hi> But there are a greater number of the people that diſagree with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> than thoſe that agree therewith. And Ieſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 7.13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and many there be which goe in thereat: becauſe ſtraite is the gate, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is the way which leadeth vnto life, and few there be that finde it.</hi> Then he addeth <hi>the teſtimony of Martyrs:</hi> a falſe marke, for there ſhall neuer be any Martyrs found, that died for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon Saints, or for Tranſubſtantiation, or for Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; They ſuffered death for the doctrine of the Goſpell, for the which our poore Churches haue ſuffered ſo many mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdomes by meanes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no more, but maketh martyrs ſuffer. For a third marke, he placeth <hi>the authority of the Fathers:</hi> But the Fathers are contrary to the Doctrine of the Romiſh <hi>Church,</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11469:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> cannot looke into them: And Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſpeaketh by heare-ſay: for in his Booke he alledgeth but foure or fiue places out of the Fathers, which are not found to be falſe and corrupted. For a fourth marke, hee puts <hi>the eminence of the Doctrine.</hi> I thinke that by the eminence, hee vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the excellency, which conſiſteth in purity, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Word of God. Without proofe to ſay, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the purity of Doctrine, it is without proofe to pre-ſuppoſe that which is in queſtion. To the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary we haue proued, againſt Maſter <hi>Arnoux,</hi> that Poperie is a heape of errours, and a corruption of Chriſtianitie. And how ſhould the people know that purity of Doctrine, ſeeing they hide the rule of purity, which is the holy Scriptures from them?</p>
               <p>For the laſt marke, hee ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth <hi>ſucceſſion, neuer interrupted.</hi> It he vnderſtandeth a ſucceſſion of doctrine, wee deny it; if he vnderſtandeth a ſucceſſion of chaires without Doctrine, that ſucceſſion is nothing. Many other Churches alſo which condemne the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> haue their ſucceſſion, and that ancienter than the <hi>Romane.</hi> And ſchiſmes haue often bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhopricke. And how can the people know any thing touching this ſucceſſion, which cannot be learned but by reading of infinite Hiſtories, and Greeke and Latine Authors, that haue written for the ſpace of one thouſand ſixe hundred yeares?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The fourth Euaſion.</head>
               <p>THe aduerſary noteth another Euaſion, wherewith wee ſerue our turnes (as he ſaith;) which is, to produce diuers places of Scripture, one with another, whereof the one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to interpret the other. For example, he ſaith, that wee expound theſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> by this place, <hi>I am the Vine:</hi> wherein hee ſlandereth vs. We know well, that theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11469:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> words, <hi>I am the Vine,</hi> are not the expoſition of theſe words, <hi>This is my body:</hi> Wee note not thoſe places. <hi>I am the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, I am the dore, This cup is the Couenant. The rocke was Chriſt,</hi> to interpret theſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> but to ſhew that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will alwaies take the words of the holy Scripture lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and leaue theſe interpretations whereby the Scripture expreſſeth it ſelfe, ſhould often fall into great abſurdities, and to ſhew that ordinarily the Scripture nameth the ſignes and Sacraments, by the names of that which they repreſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The fift Euaſion.</head>
               <p>THe fift Euaſion which Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> imputeth vnto vs, is a Chaos of confuſed calumniations. He ſaith that we attribute things to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſhee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not. That we charge the Popes with injuries. That wee reiect the originall Text of the Scripture, <hi>that is,</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew and the Greeke. That we ſay, that a Verſe is ſliden from the Margent to the Text. That wee reiect the common tranſlation, receiued by all the Fathers. That we adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and take away from the holy Scriptures. That wee forge metaphors, and improprieties of phraſes. That we eſteeme that to be ſpoken <hi>per Ironia,</hi> which is ſaid vpon oath, that we tye a conditionall particle, to a period, to draw it from the abſolute ſenſe thereof, and make thirty manifeſt places of the Scripture intricate by one obſcure place.</p>
               <p>This cart of confuſed calumniations, without any proofes, deſerueth no anſwere. It is an eaſie thing to ſpeake euill of a man without any proofe. And I beleeue that Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> hath made a collection of faults, (wherein the Doctors of the Romiſh <hi>Church</hi> are culpable,) to impoſe them vpon vs: for in Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> Booke wee finde that in euery place hee changeth our beliefe, and maketh vs ſay things which wee abhorre as much as he doth.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11469:17"/>
               <p>Hee knoweth, or ought to know, that the Doctors and Writers of the Romiſh <hi>Church,</hi> ſay and ſpeake a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand iniuries of Popes, and deteſt their liues and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>He knoweth that the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome reiecteth the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall text of the Bible, which is the Greek &amp; the Hebrew, and preferreth the vulgar tranſlation before it, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is ſo much corrupted, that if you compare the vulgar tranſlation with the Hebrew, you will ſay that there is no Booke in the world ſo badly tranſlated. <hi>Sixtus Seuenſis,</hi> the Popes keeper of his Library, acknowledgeth the ſame, in the ſeauenth Booke of the Library,<note n="*" place="margin">Hereſ. prima, Editionis vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, p. <hi>921.</hi> &amp; <hi>92<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Vulgata edito quae Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymi eſſe dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in multis à Graeca veritate diſtat.</note> where hee ſaith, that the vulgar Edition, which is ſaid to be Saint <hi>Hieromes,</hi> in many things differeth from the truth of the Greeke. That which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> acknowledgeth, is ſo farre<note n="a" place="margin">Bell. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Verbo Dei. ca. <hi>2.</hi> Heretici huic temporis odio editionis vulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae nimium tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buunt editioni Hebraicae &amp;c.</note> from accuſing vs of reiecting the Hebrew or Greeke Text, that to the contrary he accuſeth vs of holding too much with it, and of referring too much vnto it. Heretiques (ſaith hee) in hatred of the vulgar Edition, attribute too much to the Hebrew Edition. For <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Kemnitius</hi> will haue all examined and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Hebrew Text. To the contrary hee<note n="b" place="margin">Eodem. cap. <hi>2.</hi> §. His ergo. Scripturas He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braicas non eſſe in vniuerſ. deprauatas ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vel malitia Iudaeorum, nec tamen eſſe om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino integras.</note> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that the Scripture in the Hebrew is corrupted in many places, and contradicteth the opinions of <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> that will haue the Latine tranſlation to be examined and corrected by the Hebrew and the Greeke:<note n="c" place="margin">Cap. <hi>11.</hi> Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſcripturarum anteponendi ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulis verſionem, quando conſtat fontes non eſſe turbatos. Nunc autem fontes multis locis tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidos fluere iam ante oſtendinus.</note> For he will haue the vulgar tranſlation to be preferred before the Greeke and Hebrew; And that men ſhould haue their recourſe to the little Riuers, becauſe the ſpring is troubled. But thoſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, that haue ſome remnant of equity in them, and that plainely perceiue that this opinion is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Atheiſme, and maketh nothing certaine in the Word of God, ioyne themſelues with vs, and not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the vulgar tranſlation, as <hi>Sixtus Seuenſis</hi> aforeſaid, but alſo they themſelues haue made tranſlations of the Bible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Hebrew, as <hi>Sanctes Pagninus,</hi> a Luquois Monke, and <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> a Spaniard; between the which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11469:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> tranſlations, and that which is vſed in our Churches, there is great conformity.</p>
               <p>Whereas Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſaith, that the vulgar tranſlation hath beene receiued of all the Fathers, hee ſheweth, that hee neuer lookt into the Fathers; for in Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> there are two thouſand places of the holy Scriptures alledged in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words than they are ſet downe in the vulgar tranſlation. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> vſeth a different tranſlation from all the reſt; and in <hi>Hierome</hi> we haue diuers places of the old Teſtament, by him truely tranſlated according to the Hebrew; and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in the tenth Chapter of his ſecond Booke <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei,</hi> ſaith, that the vulgar tranſlation began to be receiued in the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, <hi>that is,</hi> ſixe hundred yeares after Ieſus Chriſt. And Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> acknowledgeth, that in his time, the diuerſity of Latine tranſlations were infinite, in the ſecond Booke of Chriſtian Doctrine, Chapter 11.</p>
               <p>In all theſe things,<note place="margin">De Doctr. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae, l. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> as alſo in the reſt of the ſmaller calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations, which he ſetteth downe, he ſheweth, that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what we ſay, nor what he himſelfe ſaith: and that he hath no knowledge of antiquity, nor of the nature of our Controuerſies, and had done wiſely, if hee had ſhewed his Booke to men of ſome iudgement, before he publiſhed the ſame, in ſtead of taking all his defence out of Father <hi>Gontri,</hi> without any other examination, which Ieſuite, if he were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, would aske for his feathers againe, and ſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arnoux</hi> ſhould be ſtarke naked.</p>
               <p>The reproach which hee giueth vs; to take from the Scriptures, without telling wherein and how it is done, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely in the mouthes of thoſe that from the Law of God cut off a whole Commaundement, <hi>that is,</hi> the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, wherein the worſhipping of Images is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited.</p>
               <p>But we muſt of force ſay ſomething touching the reproach which he giueth vs, that we attribute things to the Romiſh <hi>Church,</hi> which ſhe beleeueth not.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11469:18"/>
               <p>To auoid this blame, in the defence of our confeſſion of the faith, againſt Maſter <hi>Arnoux,</hi> I haue drawne our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries beliefe from the Councels of the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, and ſpecially from the Councell of Trent: as alſo from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Canons of Popes, and from the Text of the Maſſe. And where there is any diſcord betweene our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, I haue not hidden it, to the end, that an error which belongeth but to one part of the Romiſh <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould not be imputed to the whole body thereof. And if I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged any particular Doctors, they are ſome of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableſt, at the fore-front of whoſe writings, the approbation of the Doctors, and of the faculties of Theologie, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
               <p>In controuerſies of Religion, to impute contrary things to the aduerſe party, which he beleeueth not, is expreſly to make warre againſt God, and to feare that the truth ſhould be knowne, <hi>that is,</hi> to make controuerſies where none are, as if wee had not true controuerſies enough, without forged falſe controuerſies. It is a confeſſion of a bad cauſe, and an acknowledging of the truth of the contrary opinion, when before wee ſpeake againſt it, wee ſeeke to diſguiſe it. To be ſhort, it is a confeſſing that if the opinion of the Aduerſaries were truely propounded, it could not be contradicted. Or if any man doth it without malice, he ſheweth that hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth common ſenſe, to content himſelfe to learne the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of his aduerſaries, by their enemies inuectiues, or by popular report, rather than by their owne confeſſion. Whereby it happeneth that all the diſputation is a manner of skirmiſhing in the ayre, which ſtriketh no man, and a fantaſie of an imaginary controuerſie, forged, to ſtorme or beſtirre themſelues againſt.</p>
               <p>But this is the manner which at this day they vſe with vs, for they that preach, or write againſt vs, make vs as blacke as Pitch with ſlanders, and forge another confeſſion for vs. When wee reade our Aduerſaries writings, wee might ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that they write againſt another Religion than ours, if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11469:18"/> we ſaw not our names at the beginning of their Bookes, and in the titles of the Chapters. And what proteſtations ſoeuer wee make that we beleeue nothing that they make vs to ſay, yet they are reſolute, and will perſwade vs that wee doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it. Maſter <hi>Arnoux</hi> Booke written againſt our confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iuſtifieth the ſame, which in ſtead of refuting our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, changeth it, in ſuch manner, that fighting againſt his owne inuentions, his quarrell is againſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, I am forced in a briefe Table to ſet downe what kinde of confeſſion of the faith our Aduerſaries attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto vs: and how they paint out our confeſſion like a horrible Monſter, which they ſhew vnto the people to get money thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Cotton</hi> the Ieſuite, made a Booke intituled <hi>Catholique Inſtitution:</hi> at the beginning whereof, hee hath made a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to thoſe of the pretended reformed <hi>Church,</hi> wherein hee comprehendeth all our beliefe in 28. Articles, which are theſe that follow:</p>
               <p n="1">1 THat the Children of Chriſtians may be ſaued onely by the faith of their Parents, without baptiſme, and therefore that baptiſme is not abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That the Bread in the Supper of our Lord is onely the figure of the Body of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That the Church may erre.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That we muſt not allow of any traditions.</p>
               <p n="5">5 That Angels and Saints which are in glory, know not our neceſſities, and cannot heare our prayers.</p>
               <p n="6">6 That Prieſts and religious perſons may breake their vowes.</p>
               <p n="7">7 That ſingle life is not to bee preferred before mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
               <p n="8">8 That the Bookes of <hi>Macabees, Wiſdome, Eccleſiasticus, Tobias,</hi> the reſt of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Baruc,</hi> are Apocripha.</p>
               <p n="9">9 That the Soule of the Sonne of God did not deſcend into Hell, to fetch the ſoules of the holy Fathers from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11469:19"/> thence, which there ſtayed for his comming, or that before the Aſcenſion of Ieſus Chriſt, the ſoules of the Saints were receiued into Heauen, &amp; not into <hi>Limbus,</hi> nor into any other third place.</p>
               <p n="10">10 That we muſt confeſſe our ſinnes to God onely.</p>
               <p n="11">11 That faith onely iuſtifieth.</p>
               <p n="12">12 That when the fault of ſinne is remitted, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo is remitted.</p>
               <p n="13">13 That God did not create men in one and the ſame condition, but that he created ſome to be ſaued, and the reſt to be damned perpetually.</p>
               <p n="14">14 That euery particular man hath an Angell that watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ouer him.</p>
               <p n="15">15 That it is not lawfull to ſalute him, nor to call vpon him.</p>
               <p n="16">16 That God doth not ſuffer ſinne to be done, but that he will haue it to be done, that hee thruſteth vs forward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and conſtraineth vs thereunto.</p>
               <p n="17">17 That the Scripture is eaſie to be vnderſtood, and that the vnderſtanding thereof is giuen vnto all men.</p>
               <p n="18">18 That there needes no ordinary or extraordinary vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to preach the Word of God.</p>
               <p n="19">19 That we muſt beleeue nothing but that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
               <p n="20">20 That God hath not giuen power to the <hi>Church</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="21">21 That all ſinnes are mortall.</p>
               <p n="22">22 That a man cannot merit by grace.</p>
               <p n="23">23 That it is impoſſible to keepe the Commaundements of God, although he ayde vs.</p>
               <p n="24">24 That God doth not recompence good workes.</p>
               <p n="25">25 That there is no diſtinction of bleſſedneſſe among the Saints, and that they are all equall therein.</p>
               <p n="26">26 That we muſt not vſe the impoſition of hands which the Apoſtles vſed vpon thoſe of <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27 That the precept to annoynt ſicke perſons with oyle,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11469:19"/> whereof S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, ought not to be practiſed in the <hi>Church,</hi> although it was vſed by the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="28">28 That prayer for the dead was not vſed in ancient times, nor yet in the <hi>Machabees</hi> time.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe eight &amp; twenty Articles, he asketh vs proofes out of the holy Scriptures, but he ſhould aske proofes of all theſe Articles of thoſe that beleeue ſuch things, and not of vs to whom all theſe poynts are in a manner ſlanderouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. Vpon the which I will briefly ſay ſomething to the Reader, and run ouer all theſe Articles.</p>
               <p n="1">1 IT is falſe that we ſay that Children may be ſaued onely by the faith of their Parents: Touching the neceſſity of Baptiſme with water, the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome beleeueth it not. The Councell of Trent is of opinion that a vow ſupplyeth the want of Baptiſme with water, and our Aduerſaries ſay, that the Baptiſme of bloud, and the Baptiſme of the Spirit, <hi>that is,</hi> martyrdome, and regeneration, without baptiſme with water, may ſaue a man.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It is falſe that wee beleeue that the Bread in the holy Supper is onely the figure of the body of Chriſt. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth vs, that the Sacraments alſo are ſeales to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and that the bread which wee breake, is the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is falſe that we ſimply ſay that the <hi>Church</hi> can erre: The <hi>Church</hi> that is ſpoken of in the Creede, which is the <hi>Church</hi> of the Elect, cannot erre in deciding of the doubts in faith, becauſe it neuer aſſembleth to decide any thing. Touching the viſible vniuerſall <hi>Church,</hi> it was aſſembled in the perſons of the Apoſtles, which did wholly gouerne it; then it could not erre. Now it is diuided into particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>Churches;</hi> ſeperated from communion. It is impoſsible to aſſemble the ſame to decide any cauſes. Touching parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Churches,</hi> as the Greeke, Romane, and the Syrian, &amp;c. There are ſome that may erre, and there are ſome particular
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11469:20"/> 
                  <hi>Churches</hi> wherein it is impoſsible to be ſaued, <hi>that is,</hi> thoſe that are idolatrous, where the benefit of Ieſus Chriſt is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
               <p n="4">4 It is falſe, that we reiect all traditions, we reiect thoſe onely, which add ſomething to the doctrine of faith, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="5">5 It is falſe, that we beleeue that Angels and Saints, know not our neceſſities, they doe generally know, that the Church of God is perſecuted, and hath great combats to reſiſt. The Angels that God hath appointed to be our gardians, know our neceſſities, and what eſtate we are in.</p>
               <p n="6">6 It is falſe, that we ſimply ſay, that Prieſts ought not to keepe their vowes, if they make a vow of poſſible things, and conformable to the Word of God, they ought to keepe them.</p>
               <p n="7">7 It is falſe that we ſay, that ſingle life is not to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before marriage; ſingle life that is continent, and hath no euill deſires, hath great commodities and aduantages aboue marriage, and more liberty to ſerue God.</p>
               <p n="8">8. 9. The eighth and ninth Articles are true, wee reiect the <hi>Limbus patrum,</hi> which is ſaid to bee emptie theſe 1600. yeeres, and the Apocriphall bookes.</p>
               <p n="10">10 It is falſe, that we ſay, that we muſt confeſſe our ſinnes onely to God. We muſt confeſſe them to the Church, and to our Paſtors, and to our neighbours whom wee haue offended.</p>
               <p n="11">11 To take the word iuſtifie, in that ſenſe which our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries take it, for regeneration and ſanctification; It is falſe that we ſay, that faith onely iuſtifieth. For a Chriſtian is regenerated by all Chriſtian vertues. But if by being iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied they vnderſtand abſolued, and eſteemed to be righteous before the iudiciall ſeate of God (which is the ſenſe wherein the Scripture ordinarily taketh the word iuſtifie) in that ſenſe, we ſay, that faith voide of workes, cannot iuſtifie vs: but that faith accompanied with workes, onely hath the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to iuſtifie vs; for that among Chriſtian vertues, faith one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11469:20"/> hath that propertie; To apprehend the benefit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="12">12 It is falſe that we ſimply ſay, without exception, that when the fault is remitted, the puniſhment alſo is remitted. We ſpeake that of ſatisfactory, and vindicatiue puniſhments: but not of chaſtning puniſhments which ſerue to amend and inſtruſt the ſinner in time to come. Thoſe puniſhments are ſufferable with the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="13">13 It is falſe that we ſay, that God hath created men to be damned, <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith not ſo, and if hee had ſaid ſo, wee are not bound to beleeue it.</p>
               <p n="14">14 It is falſe that we ſay, that euery one of vs hath not an Angell to be his guardian. Our Churches haue not defined any thing touching that point. Whether God imployeth an Angell for the guarding of diuers perſons, or many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels for the guarding of one man: It is a thing which wee leaue to the Counſell of God.</p>
               <p n="15">15 The fifteenth Article is true, we honour Saints, and ſet them before vs for an example, and aſpire to their beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but we call not vpon them.</p>
               <p n="16">16 It is falſe and ſlanderous that we ſay, that God thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth vs forward and conſtraineth vs to ſinne; that doctrine is horrible and diueliſh. <hi>Caluin</hi> to whom they impute this doctrine, neuer ſaid it, but taught the contrary, and although he had ſaid it, yet our confeſſion of the faith in the ſeauenth Article, proteſteth the contrary in theſe words, ſaying; Not that God is the Author of euill, or that the fault can be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, ſeeing that his will is the ſoueraigne and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule of all doctrine and equitie.</p>
               <p n="17">17 It is falſe that we ſay, that the Scripture is eaſie to bee vnderſtood, and that the vnderſtanding thereof is giuen vnto all men. In it there are obſcure propheſies, and difficult pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. We ſay that in the Scriptures there are ſufficient, euident and cleare places which are inſtructions vnto vs for ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that in things which are plaine and manifeſt in the Scriptures, and which haue no neede of interpretation, all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:11469:21"/> that which is neceſſary for our ſaluation, is contayned.</p>
               <p n="18">18 It is falſe that we ſay, that to preach the Word of God there needes no ordinary nor extraordinary calling. I haue made a booke expreſly to proue the contrary.</p>
               <p n="19">19 It is falſe that we ſay, that we muſt beleeue nothing but that which is written. We ſay, that we muſt not receiue any doctrine, (as neceſſary to ſaluation) that is not contained in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p n="20">20 It is falſe that we ſay, that God hath not giuen power to the Church to remit ſinnes; faithfull Paſtors haue that power, but their pardon is conditionall, ſo the party be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant ſinner, which is not certanely knowne, but to God onely. Therefore their iudgement muſt of force be conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall. As the holy Scripture ſaith that Paſtors ſaue ſoules, becauſe God vſeth their miniſtry to ſaue them, ſo it ſaith, that Paſtors pardon ſinnes, becauſe God vſeth their meanes to pardon them.</p>
               <p n="21">21 It is falſe that our Churches haue made any definition touching this point, that all ſinnes are mortall: It belongeth not to criminals and ſinners to determine what puniſhment euery ſinne they commit deſerueth. Onely we reiect that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction which is made betweene mortall and veniall ſinnes; that is, pardonable: becauſe thoſe ſinnes which are called mortall, are pardonable in thoſe that conuert and amend their liues, and thoſe ſinnes that are called veniall, are mortall when men perſeuere therein till they die, and that contempt and finall obſtinacy is added to the tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p n="22">22 The 22. Article is true, We doe not preſume that wee can merit before God, and if thereupon we ſhould be asked, whether we cannot merit by the grace of God? I anſwere that the ſame grace is it which hindereth vs from meriting. For, for that cauſe our good workes are not meritorious, becauſe they proceed from the grace of God. It is no merit to receiue grace.</p>
               <p n="23">23 It is falſe that we ſay, that it is impoſſible to keepe the commandements of God, though God doth helpe vs. When
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11469:21"/> it is the will of God to make a man perfect, and without ſinne, no man can hinder it, nor limit any rules to the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his Spirit.</p>
               <p n="24">24 It is moſt falſe that we ſay, that God doth not reward good workes.</p>
               <p n="25">25 It is falſe that we hold, for a moſt aſſured thing, that the Saints haue equall glory in heauen. That is no Article neceſſary to ſaluation, we condemne no man for that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuffer euery man to conceiue thereof as hee thinketh it moſt probable. But the Pope which giueth a degree of glory vnto ſome men aboue the vulgar Saints, is bound to maintaine that inequalitie.</p>
               <p n="26">26 It is falſe that we ſay, that we muſt not vſe the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands which the Apoſtles vſed in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and in <hi>Epheſus:</hi> Whoſoeuer hath the vertue by impoſition of hands to conferre the ſame miraculous graces, and the gift of tongues, which the Apoſtles conferred, ſhall doe well to vſe that ceremony.</p>
               <p n="27">27 It is falſe that we ſay, That the precept to annoynt the ſicke with oyle, whereof S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, ought not to be practiſed in the Church; Wee know, that not onely the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but alſo their diſciples after them, did profitably vſe the ſame, for healing of the ſicke: Whoſoeuer can by that vnction doe the like miraculous effects, ſhall doe well to vſe the ſame ceremony.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Laſtly, it is falſe, that our Churches beleeue and teach that prayer for the dead was not anciently in vſe. Wee ſay, that the firſt ages, whoſe examples ſhould ſerue vs for a Law, vſed it not, and that God did not ordaine it. Touching the <hi>Machabees,</hi> it concernes vs nothing to know, whether that as then they prayed for the dead: For although the bookes of the <hi>Machabees</hi> are full of fables, and that the ſame hiſtory is to be ſuſpected, yet although it were true, our Religion is not ruled by the Iewes actions, but by the commandement of God, as alſo that prayer for the dead, whereof wee ſpeake, is made with a reference to the reſurrection, and not to draw ſoules out of Purgatory.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:11469:22"/>
               <p>The indifferent Reader will conſider, with what people wee haue to doe, ſeeing that of the 28. Articles, wherein they comprehend our Religion, there are but foure which truely and without calumniation doe repreſent our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: and what hope is there, to end our Controuerſies by the Word of God, ſeeing that they binde vs by the Word of God to proue thoſe things which we beleeue not. How ſhould they faithfully propound our beleefe to their people, when they diſguiſe it vnto vs? Put the caſe that our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were as full of errors, as it is holy, iuſt, and true: why doe they inſteed of ſeeking to draw vs out of errours, goe about to drowne vs therein? why doe they ſtudy to make vs worſe, inſteed of amending or bettering vs? or doe they thinke, that wee haue forgotten our Religion, and that wee muſt be forc't to come to them to learne it? Wee are vſed in the like manner by the Biſhop of <hi>Luzon,</hi> in his booke that he hath made againſt our Epiſtle dedicated to the King. In the tenth page, hee reduceth our Religion into twelue Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which he hath forged out of ſome places of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which he hath clipt, and which doe not ſay that which he would haue them to ſay, which we take for a iuſtification of our cauſe, ſeeing that no man dares encounter with vs face to face, nor come directly to vs, but all of them take a wrong courſe, and goe by-as way, and diſcharge not their choller againſt our Religion, but againſt another, which they haue forged at their pleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11469:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
